q-1:
  question: "What is your only comfort in life and death?"
  answer:
    - "That I am not my own, ^1 but belong with body and soul, both in life and in death, ^2 to my faithful Saviour Jesus Christ. ^3"
    - "He has fully paid for all my sins with his precious blood, ^4 and has set me free from all the power of the devil. ^5"
    - "He also preserves me in such a way ^6 that without the will of my heavenly Father not a hair can fall from my head; ^7 indeed, all things must work together for my salvation. ^8"
    - "Therefore, by his Holy Spirit he also assures me of eternal life ^9 and makes me heartily willing and ready from now on to live for him. ^10"
  refs:
    - ["1 Cor 6:19-20"]
    - ["Rom 14:7-9"]
    - ["1 Cor 3:23", "Tit 2:14"]
    - ["1 Pet 1:18-19", "1 Jn 1:7", "1 Jn 2:2"]
    - ["Jn 8:34-36", "Heb 2:14-15", "1 Jn 3:8"]
    - ["Jn 6:39-40", "Jn 10:27-30", "2 Thess 3:3", "1 Pet 1:5"]
    - ["Mt 10:29-31", "Lk 21:16-18"]
    - ["Rom 8:28"]
    - ["Rom 8:15-16", "2 Cor 1:21-22", "2 Cor 5:5", "Eph 1:13-14"]
    - ["Rom 8:14"]

q-2:
  question: "What do you need to know in order to live and die in the joy of this comfort?"
  answer:
    - "First, how great my sins and misery are; ^1"
    - "second, how I am delivered from all my sins and misery; ^2"
    - "third, how I am to be thankful to God for such deliverance. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Rom 3:9-10", "1 Jn 1:10"]
    - ["Jn 17:3", "Acts 4:12", "Acts 10:43"]
    - ["Mt 5:16", "Rom 6:13", "Eph 5:8-10", "1 Pet 2:9-10"]

q-3:
  question: "From where do you know your sins and misery?"
  answer:
    - "From the law of God. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Rom 3:20", "Rom 7:7-25"]

q-4:
  question: "What does God's law require of us?"
  answer:
    - "Christ teaches us this in a summary in Matthew 22:"
    - "Love the Lord your God with all your heart and with all your soul and with all your mind. ^1 This is the first and greatest commandment."
    - "And the second is like it: Love your neighbour as yourself. All the Law and the Prophets hang on these two commandments. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Deut 6:5"]
    - ["Lev 19:18"]

q-5:
  question: "Can you keep all this perfectly?"
  answer:
    - "No, ^1 I am inclined by nature to hate God and my neighbour. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Rom 3:10", "Rom 3:23", "1 Jn 1:8", "1 Jn 1:10"]
    - ["Gen 6:5", "Gen 8:21", "Jer 17:9", "Rom 7:23", "Rom 8:7", "Eph 2:3", "Tit 3:3"]

q-6:
  question: "Did God, then, create man so wicked and perverse?"
  answer:
    - "No, on the contrary, God created man good ^1 and in his image, ^2 that is, in true righteousness and holiness, ^3 so that he might rightly know God his Creator, ^4 heartily love him, and live with him in eternal blessedness to praise and glorify him. ^5"
  refs:
    - ["Gen 1:31"]
    - ["Gen 1:26-27"]
    - ["Eph 4:24"]
    - ["Col 3:10"]
    - ["Ps 8"]

q-7:
  question: "From where, then, did man's depraved nature come?"
  answer:
    - "From the fall and disobedience of our first parents, Adam and Eve, in Paradise, ^1 for there our nature became so corrupt ^2 that we are all conceived and born in sin. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Gen 3"]
    - ["Rom 5:12", "Rom 5:18-19"]
    - ["Ps 51:5"]

q-8:
  question: "But are we so corrupt that we are totally unable to do any good and inclined to all evil?"
  answer:
    - "Yes, ^1 unless we are regenerated by the Spirit of God. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Gen 6:5", "Gen 8:21", "Job 14:4", "Is 53:6"]
    - ["Jn 3:3-5"]

q-9:
  question: "But does not God do man an injustice by requiring in his law what man cannot do?"
  answer:
    - "No, for God so created man that he was able to do it. ^1 But man, at the instigation of the devil, ^2 in deliberate disobedience ^3 robbed himself and all his descendants of these gifts. ^4"
  refs:
    - ["Gen 1:31"]
    - ["Gen 3:13", "Jn 8:44", "1 Tim 2:13-14"]
    - ["Gen 3:6"]
    - ["Rom 5:12", "Rom 5:18-19"]

q-10:
  question: "Will God allow such disobedience and apostasy to go unpunished?"
  answer:
    - "Certainly not."
    - "He is terribly displeased with our original sin as well as our actual sins."
    - "Therefore he will punish them by a just judgment both now and eternally, ^1 as he has declared: ^2"
    - "Cursed is everyone who does not continue to do everything written in the Book of the Law. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Gen 2:17", "Ex 34:7", "Ps 5:4-6", "Ps 7:11", "Nahum 1:2", "Rom 1:18", "Rom 5:12", "Eph 5:6", "Heb 9:27"]
    - ["Deut 27:26"]
    - ["Gal 3:10"]

q-11:
  question: "But is God not also merciful?"
  answer:
    - "God is indeed merciful, ^1 but he is also just. ^2"
    - "His justice requires that sin committed against the most high majesty of God also be punished with the most severe, that is, with everlasting, punishment of body and soul. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Ex 20:6", "Ex 34:6-7", "Ps 103:8-9"]
    - ["Ex 20:5", "Ex 34:7", "Deut 7:9-11", "Ps 5:4-6", "Heb 10:30-31"]
    - ["Mt 25:45-46"]

q-12:
  question: "Since, according to God's righteous judgment we deserve temporal and eternal punishment, how can we escape this punishment and be again received into favour?"
  answer:
    - "God demands that his justice be satisfied. ^1 Therefore we must make full payment, either by ourselves or through another. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Ex 20:5", "Ex 23:7", "Rom 2:1-11"]
    - ["Is 53:11", "Rom 8:3-4"]

q-13:
  question: "Can we by ourselves make this payment?"
  answer:
    - "Certainly not."
    - "On the contrary, we daily increase our debt. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Ps 130:3", "Mt 6:12", "Rom 2:4-5"]

q-14:
  question: "Can any mere creature pay for us?"
  answer:
    - "No."
    - "In the first place, God will not punish another creature for the sin which man has committed. ^1 Furthermore, no mere creature can sustain the burden of God's eternal wrath against sin and deliver others from it. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Ezek 18:4", "Ezek 18:20", "Heb 2:14-18"]
    - ["Ps 130:3", "Nahum 1:6"]

q-15:
  question: "What kind of mediator and deliverer must we seek?"
  answer:
    - "One who is a true ^1 and righteous ^2 man, and yet more powerful than all creatures; that is, one who is at the same time true God. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["1 Cor 15:21", "Heb 2:17"]
    - ["Is 53:9", "2 Cor 5:21", "Heb 7:26"]
    - ["Is 7:14", "Is 9:6", "Jer 23:6", "Jn 1:1", "Rom 8:3-4"]

q-16:
  question: "Why must he be a true and righteous man?"
  answer:
    - "He must be a true man because the justice of God requires that the same human nature which has sinned should pay for sin. ^1 He must be a righteous man because one who himself is a sinner cannot pay for others. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Rom 5:12", "Rom 5:15", "1 Cor 15:21", "Heb 2:14-16"]
    - ["Heb 7:26-27", "1 Pet 3:18"]

q-17:
  question: "Why must he at the same time be true God?"
  answer:
    - "He must be true God so that by the power of his divine nature ^1 he might bear in his human nature the burden of God's wrath, ^2 and might obtain for us and restore to us righteousness and life. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Is 9:6"]
    - ["Deut 4:24", "Nahum 1:6", "Ps 130:3"]
    - ["Is 53:5", "Is 53:11", "Jn 3:16", "2 Cor 5:21"]

q-18:
  question: "But who is that Mediator who at the same time is true God and a true and righteous man?"
  answer:
    - "Our Lord Jesus Christ, ^1 who has become for us wisdom from God – that is, our righteousness, holiness and redemption. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 1:21-23", "Lk 2:11", "1 Tim 2:5", "1 Tim 3:16"]
    - ["1 Cor 1:30"]

q-19:
  question: "From where do you know this?"
  answer:
    - "From the holy gospel, which God himself first revealed in Paradise. ^1 Later, he had it proclaimed by the patriarchs ^2 and prophets, ^3 and foreshadowed by the sacrifices and other ceremonies of the law. ^4 Finally, he had it fulfilled through his only Son. ^5"
  refs:
    - ["Gen 3:15"]
    - ["Gen 12:3", "Gen 22:18", "Gen 49:10"]
    - ["Is 53", "Jer 23:5-6", "Mic 7:18-20", "Acts 10:43", "Heb 1:1"]
    - ["Lev 1-7", "Jn 5:46", "Heb 10:1-10"]
    - ["Rom 10:4", "Gal 4:4-5", "Col 2:17"]

q-20:
  question: "Are all men, then, saved by Christ just as they perished through Adam?"
  answer:
    - "No. Only those are saved who by a true faith are grafted into Christ and accept all his benefits. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 7:14", "Jn 1:12", "Jn 3:16", "Jn 3:18", "Jn 3:36", "Rom 11:16-21"]

q-21:
  question: "What is true faith?"
  answer:
    - "True faith is a sure knowledge whereby I accept as true all that God has revealed to us in his Word. ^1 At the same time it is a firm confidence ^2 that not only to others, but also to me, ^3 God has granted forgiveness of sins, everlasting righteousness, and salvation, ^4 out of mere grace, only for the sake of Christ's merits. ^5 This faith the Holy Spirit works in my heart by the gospel. ^6"
  refs:
    - ["Jn 17:3", "Jn 17:17", "Heb 11:1-3", "Jas 2:19"]
    - ["Rom 4:18-21", "Rom 5:1", "Rom 10:10", "Heb 4:16"]
    - ["Gal 2:20"]
    - ["Rom 1:17", "Heb 10:10"]
    - ["Rom 3:20-26", "Gal 2:16", "Eph 2:8-10"]
    - ["Acts 16:14", "Rom 1:16", "Rom 10:17", "1 Cor 1:21"]

q-22:
  question: "What, then, must a Christian believe?"
  answer:
    - "All that is promised us in the gospel, ^1 which the articles of our catholic and undoubted Christian faith teach us in a summary."
  refs:
    - ["Mt 28:19", "Jn 20:30-31"]

q-23:
  question: "What are these articles?"
  answer:
    - "Part I \\ 1. I believe in God the Father almighty, Creator of heaven and earth."
    - "Part II \\ 2. I believe in Jesus Christ, his only-begotten Son, our Lord;"
    - "3. he was conceived by the Holy Spirit, born of the virgin Mary;"
    - "4. suffered under Pontius Pilate, was crucified, dead, and buried; he descended into hell."
    - "5. On the third day he arose from the dead;"
    - "6. he ascended into heaven, and sits at the right hand of God the Father almighty;"
    - "7. from there he will come to judge the living and the dead."
    - "Part III \\ 8. I believe in the Holy Spirit;"
    - "9. I believe a holy catholic Christian church, the communion of saints;"
    - "10. the forgiveness of sins;"
    - "11. the resurrection of the body;"
    - "12. and the life everlasting."
  refs: []

q-24:
  question: "How are these articles divided?"
  answer:
    - "Into three parts: the first is about God the Father and our creation; the second about God the Son and our redemption; the third about God the Holy Spirit and our sanctification."
  refs: []

q-25:
  question: "Since there is only one God, ^1 why do you speak of three persons, Father, Son, and Holy Spirit?"
  answer:
    - "Because God has so revealed himself in his Word ^2 that these three distinct persons are the one, true, eternal God."
  refs:
    - ["Deut 6:4", "Is 44:6", "Is 45:5", "1 Cor 8:4", "1 Cor 8:6"]
    - ["Gen 1:2-3", "Is 61:1", "Is 63:8-10", "Mt 3:16-17", "Mt 28:18-19", "Lk 4:18", "Jn 14:26", "Jn 15:26", "2 Cor 13:14", "Gal 4:6", "Tit 3:5-6"]

q-26:
  question: "What do you believe when you say: I believe in God the Father almighty, Creator of heaven and earth?"
  answer:
    - "That the eternal Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who out of nothing created heaven and earth and all that is in them, ^1"
    - "and who still upholds and governs them by his eternal counsel and providence, ^2 is, for the sake of Christ his Son, my God and my Father. ^3"
    - "In him I trust so completely as to have no doubt that he will provide me with all things necessary for body and soul, ^4 and will also turn to my good whatever adversity he sends me in this life of sorrow. ^5"
    - "He is able to do so as almighty God, ^6 and willing also as a faithful Father. ^7"
  refs:
    - ["Gen 1-2", "Ex 20:11", "Job 38-39", "Ps 33:6", "Is 44:24", "Acts 4:24", "Acts 14:15"]
    - ["Ps 104:27-30", "Mt 6:30", "Mt 10:29", "Eph 1:11"]
    - ["Jn 1:12-13", "Rom 8:15-16", "Gal 4:4-7", "Eph 1:5"]
    - ["Ps 55:22", "Mt 6:25-26", "Lk 12:22-31"]
    - ["Rom 8:28"]
    - ["Gen 18:14", "Rom 8:31-39"]
    - ["Mt 6:32-33", "Mt 7:9-11"]

q-27:
  question: "What do you understand by the providence of God?"
  answer:
    - "God's providence is his almighty and ever present power, ^1 whereby, as with his hand, he still upholds heaven and earth and all creatures, ^2 and so governs them that leaf and blade, rain and drought, fruitful and barren years, food and drink, health and sickness, riches and poverty, ^3 indeed, all things, come to us not by chance ^4 but by his fatherly hand. ^5"
  refs:
    - ["Jer 23:23-24", "Acts 17:24-28"]
    - ["Heb 1:3"]
    - ["Jer 5:24", "Acts 14:15-17", "Jn 9:3", "Prov 22:2"]
    - ["Prov 16:33"]
    - ["Mt 10:29"]

q-28:
  question: "What does it benefit us to know that God has created all things and still upholds them by his providence?"
  answer:
    - "We can be patient in adversity, ^1 thankful in prosperity, ^2 and with a view to the future we can have a firm confidence in our faithful God and Father that no creature shall separate us from his love; ^3"
    - "for all creatures are so completely in his hand that without his will they cannot so much as move. ^4"
  refs:
    - ["Job 1:21-22", "Ps 39:10", "Jas 1:3"]
    - ["Deut 8:10", "1 Thess 5:18"]
    - ["Ps 55:22", "Rom 5:3-5", "Rom 8:38-39"]
    - ["Job 1:12", "Job 2:6", "Prov 21:1", "Acts 17:24-28"]

q-29:
  question: "Why is the Son of God called Jesus, that is, Saviour?"
  answer:
    - "Because he saves us from all our sins, ^1 and because salvation is not to be sought or found in anyone else. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 1:21", "Heb 7:25"]
    - ["Is 43:11", "Jn 15:4-5", "Acts 4:11-12", "1 Tim 2:5"]

q-30:
  question: "Do those who seek their salvation or well-being in saints, in themselves, or anywhere else, also believe in the only Saviour Jesus?"
  answer:
    - "No."
    - "Though they boast of him in words, they in fact deny the only Saviour Jesus. ^1"
    - "For one of two things must be true: either Jesus is not a complete Saviour, or those who by true faith accept this Saviour must find in him all that is necessary for their salvation. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["1 Cor 1:12-13", "Gal 5:4"]
    - ["Col 1:19-20", "Col 2:10", "1 Jn 1:7"]

q-31:
  question: "Why is he called Christ, that is, Anointed?"
  answer:
    - "Because he has been ordained by God the Father, and anointed with the Holy Spirit, ^1 to be our chief Prophet and Teacher, ^2 who has fully revealed to us the secret counsel and will of God concerning our redemption; ^3 our only High Priest, ^4 who by the one sacrifice of his body has redeemed us, ^5 and who continually intercedes for us before the Father; ^6 and our eternal King, ^7"
  refs:
    - ["Ps 45:7", "Heb 1:9", "Is 61:1", "Lk 4:18", "Lk 3:21-22"]
    - ["Deut 18:15", "Acts 3:22"]
    - ["Jn 1:18", "Jn 15:15"]
    - ["Ps 110:4", "Heb 7:17"]
    - ["Heb 9:12", "Heb 10:11-14"]
    - ["Rom 8:34", "Heb 9:24", "1 Jn 2:1"]
    - ["Lk 1:33", "Mt 28:18", "Jn 10:28", "Rev 12:10-11"]

q-32:
  question: "Why are you called a Christian?"
  answer:
    - "Because I am a member of Christ by faith ^1 and thus share in his anointing, ^2 so that I may as prophet confess his name, ^3 as priest present myself a living sacrifice of thankfulness to him, ^4 and as king fight with a free and good conscience against sin and the devil in this life, ^5 and hereafter reign with him eternally over all creatures. ^6"
  refs:
    - ["1 Cor 12:12-27"]
    - ["Joel 2:28", "Acts 2:17", "1 Jn 2:27"]
    - ["Mt 10:32", "Rom 10:9-10", "Heb 13:15"]
    - ["Rom 12:1", "1 Pet 2:5", "1 Pet 2:9"]
    - ["Gal 5:16-17", "Eph 6:11", "1 Tim 1:18-19"]
    - ["Mt 25:34", "2 Tim 2:12"]

q-33:
  question: "Why is he called God's only-begotten Son, since we also are children of God?"
  answer:
    - "Because Christ alone is the eternal, natural Son of God. ^1 We, however, are children of God by adoption, through grace, for Christ's sake. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Jn 1:1-3", "Jn 1:14", "Jn 1:18", "Jn 3:16", "Rom 8:32", "Heb 1", "1 Jn 4:9"]
    - ["Jn 1:12", "Rom 8:14-17", "Gal 4:6", "Eph 1:5-6"]

q-34:
  question: "Why do you call him our Lord?"
  answer:
    - "Because he has ransomed us, body and soul, ^1 from all our sins, not with silver or gold but with his precious blood, ^2 and has freed us from all the power of the devil to make us his own possession. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["1 Cor 6:20", "1 Tim 2:5-6"]
    - ["1 Pet 1:18-19"]
    - ["Col 1:13-14", "Heb 2:14-15"]

q-35:
  question: "What do you confess when you say: He was conceived by the Holy Spirit, born of the virgin Mary?"
  answer:
    - "The eternal Son of God, who is and remains true and eternal God, ^1 took upon himself true human nature from the flesh and blood of the virgin Mary, ^2 through the working of the Holy Spirit. ^3 Thus he is also the true seed of David, ^4 and like his brothers in every respect, ^5 yet without sin. ^6"
  refs:
    - ["Jn 1:1", "Jn 10:30-36", "Rom 1:3", "Rom 9:5", "Col 1:15-17", "1 Jn 5:20"]
    - ["Mt 1:18-23", "Jn 1:14", "Gal 4:4", "Heb 2:14"]
    - ["Lk 1:35"]
    - ["2 Sam 7:12-16", "Ps 132:11", "Mt 1:1", "Lk 1:32", "Rom 1:3"]
    - ["Phil 2:7", "Heb 2:17"]
    - ["Heb 4:15", "Heb 7:26-27"]

q-36:
  question: "What benefit do you receive from the holy conception and birth of Christ?"
  answer:
    - "He is our Mediator, ^1 and with his innocence and perfect holiness covers, in the sight of God, my sin, in which I was conceived and born. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["1 Tim 2:5-6", "Heb 9:13-15"]
    - ["Rom 8:3-4", "2 Cor 5:21", "Gal 4:4-5", "1 Pet 1:18-19"]

q-37:
  question: "What do you confess when you say that he suffered?"
  answer:
    - "During all the time he lived on earth, but especially at the end, Christ bore in body and soul the wrath of God against the sin of the whole human race. ^1 Thus, by his suffering, as the only atoning sacrifice, ^2 he has redeemed our body and soul from everlasting damnation, ^3 and obtained for us the grace of God, righteousness, and eternal life. ^4"
  refs:
    - ["Is 53", "1 Tim 2:6", "1 Pet 2:24", "1 Pet 3:18"]
    - ["Rom 3:25", "1 Cor 5:7", "Eph 5:2", "Heb 10:14", "1 Jn 2:2", "1 Jn 4:10"]
    - ["Rom 8:1-4", "Gal 3:13", "Col 1:13", "Heb 9:12", "1 Pet 1:18-19"]
    - ["Jn 3:16", "Rom 3:24-26", "2 Cor 5:21", "Heb 9:15"]

q-38:
  question: "Why did he suffer under Pontius Pilate as judge?"
  answer:
    - "Though innocent, Christ was condemned by an earthly judge, ^1 and so he freed us from the severe judgment of God that was to fall on us. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Lk 23:13-24", "Jn 19:4", "Jn 19:12-16"]
    - ["Is 53:4-5", "2 Cor 5:21", "Gal 3:13"]

q-39:
  question: "Does it have a special meaning that Christ was crucified and did not die in a different way?"
  answer:
    - "Yes."
    - "Thereby I am assured that he took upon himself the curse which lay on me, for a crucified one was cursed by God. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Deut 21:23", "Gal 3:13"]

q-40:
  question: "Why was it necessary for Christ to humble himself even unto death?"
  answer:
    - "Because of the justice and truth of God ^1 satisfaction for our sins could be made in no other way than by the death of the Son of God. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Gen 2:17"]
    - ["Rom 8:3", "Phil 2:8", "Heb 2:9", "Heb 2:14-15"]

q-41:
  question: "Why was he buried?"
  answer:
    - "His burial testified that he had really died. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Is 53:9", "Jn 19:38-42", "Acts 13:29", "1 Cor 15:3-4"]

q-42:
  question: "Since Christ has died for us, why do we still have to die?"
  answer:
    - "Our death is not a payment for our sins, but it puts an end to sin and is an entrance into eternal life. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Jn 5:24", "Phil 1:21-23", "1 Thess 5:9-10"]

q-43:
  question: "What further benefit do we receive from Christ's sacrifice and death on the cross?"
  answer:
    - "Through Christ's death our old nature is crucified, put to death, and buried with him, ^1 so that the evil desires of the flesh may no longer reign in us, ^2 but that we may offer ourselves to him as a sacrifice of thankfulness. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Rom 6:5-11", "Col 2:11-12"]
    - ["Rom 6:12-14"]
    - ["Rom 12:1", "Eph 5:1-2"]

q-44:
  question: "Why is there added: He descended into hell?"
  answer:
    - "In my greatest sorrows and temptations I may be assured and comforted that my Lord Jesus Christ, by his unspeakable anguish, pain, terror, and agony, which he endured throughout all his sufferings ^1 but especially on the cross, has delivered me from the anguish and torment of hell. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Ps 18:5-6", "Ps 116:3", "Mt 26:36-46", "Mt 27:45-46", "Heb 5:7-10"]
    - ["Is 53"]

q-45:
  question: "How does Christ's resurrection benefit us?"
  answer:
    - "First, by his resurrection he has overcome death, so that he could make us share in the righteousness which he had obtained for us by his death. ^1"
    - "Second, by his power we too are raised up to a new life. ^2"
    - "Third, Christ's resurrection is to us a sure pledge of our glorious resurrection. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Rom 4:25", "1 Cor 15:16-20", "1 Pet 1:3-5"]
    - ["Rom 6:5-11", "Eph 2:4-6", "Col 3:1-4"]
    - ["Rom 8:11", "1 Cor 15:12-23", "Phil 3:20-21"]

q-46:
  question: "What do you confess when you say, he ascended into heaven?"
  answer:
    - "That Christ, before the eyes of his disciples, was taken up from the earth into heaven, ^1 and that he is there for our benefit ^2 until he comes again to judge the living and the dead. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Mk 16:19", "Lk 24:50-51", "Acts 1:9-11"]
    - ["Rom 8:34", "Heb 4:14", "Heb 7:23-25", "Heb 9:24"]
    - ["Mt 24:30", "Acts 1:11"]

q-47:
  question: "Is Christ, then, not with us until the end of the world, as he has promised us? ^1"
  answer:
    - "Christ is true man and true God. With respect to his human nature he is no longer on earth, ^2 but with respect to his divinity, majesty, grace, and Spirit he is never absent from us. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 28:20"]
    - ["Mt 26:11", "Jn 16:28", "Jn 17:11", "Acts 3:19-21", "Heb 8:4"]
    - ["Mt 28:18-20", "Jn 14:16-19", "Jn 16:13"]

q-48:
  question: "But are the two natures in Christ not separated from each other if his human nature is not present wherever his divinity is?"
  answer:
    - "Not at all, for his divinity has no limits and is present everywhere. ^1 So it must follow that his divinity is indeed beyond the human nature which he has taken on and nevertheless is within this human nature and remains personally united with it. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Jer 23:23-24", "Acts 7:48-49"]
    - ["Jn 1:14", "Jn 3:13", "Col 2:9"]

q-49:
  question: "How does Christ's ascension into heaven benefit us?"
  answer:
    - "First, he is our Advocate in heaven before his Father. ^1 Second, we have our flesh in heaven as a sure pledge that he, our Head, will also take us, his members, up to himself. ^2 Third, he sends us his Spirit as a counter-pledge, ^3 by whose power we seek the things that are above, where Christ is, seated at the right hand of God, and not the things that are on earth. ^4"
  refs:
    - ["Rom 8:34", "1 Jn 2:1"]
    - ["Jn 14:2", "Jn 17:24", "Eph 2:4-6"]
    - ["Jn 14:16", "Acts 2:33", "2 Cor 1:21-22", "2 Cor 5:5"]
    - ["Col 3:1-4"]

q-50:
  question: "Why is it added, and sits at the right hand of God?"
  answer:
    - "Christ ascended into heaven to manifest himself there as Head of his church, ^1 through whom the Father governs all things. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Eph 1:20-23", "Col 1:18"]
    - ["Mt 28:18", "Jn 5:22-23"]

q-51:
  question: "How does the glory of Christ, our Head, benefit us?"
  answer:
    - "First, by his Holy Spirit he pours out heavenly gifts upon us, his members. ^1"
    - "Second, by his power he defends and preserves us against all enemies. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Acts 2:33", "Eph 4:7-12"]
    - ["Ps 2:9", "Ps 110:1-2", "Jn 10:27-30", "Rev 19:11-16"]

q-52:
  question: "What comfort is it to you that Christ will come to judge the living and the dead?"
  answer:
    - "In all my sorrow and persecution I lift up my head and eagerly await as judge from heaven the very same person who before has submitted himself to the judgment of God for my sake, and has removed all the curse from me. ^1"
    - "He will cast all his and my enemies into everlasting condemnation, but he will take me and all his chosen ones to himself into heavenly joy and glory. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Lk 21:28", "Rom 8:22-25", "Phil 3:20-21", "Tit 2:13-14"]
    - ["Mt 25:31-46", "1 Thess 4:16-17", "2 Thess 1:6-10"]

q-53:
  question: "What do you believe concerning the Holy Spirit?"
  answer:
    - "First, he is, together with the Father and the Son, true and eternal God. ^1"
    - "Second, he is also given to me, ^2 to make me by true faith share in Christ and all his benefits, ^3 to comfort me, ^4 and to remain with me forever. ^5"
  refs:
    - ["Gen 1:1-2", "Mt 28:19", "Acts 5:3-4", "1 Cor 3:16"]
    - ["1 Cor 6:19", "2 Cor 1:21-22", "Gal 4:6", "Eph 1:13"]
    - ["Gal 3:14", "1 Pet 1:2"]
    - ["Jn 15:26", "Acts 9:31"]
    - ["Jn 14:16-17", "1 Pet 4:14"]

q-54:
  question: "What do you believe concerning the holy catholic Christian church?"
  answer:
    - "I believe that the Son of God, ^1 out of the whole human race, ^2 from the beginning of the world to its end, ^3 gathers, defends, and preserves for himself, ^4 by his Spirit and Word, ^5 in the unity of the true faith, ^6 a church chosen to everlasting life. ^7"
    - "And I believe that I am ^8 and forever shall remain a living member of it. ^9"
  refs:
    - ["Jn 10:11", "Acts 20:28", "Eph 4:11-13", "Col 1:18"]
    - ["Gen 26:4", "Rev 5:9"]
    - ["Is 59:21", "1 Cor 11:26"]
    - ["Ps 129:1-5", "Mt 16:18", "Jn 10:28-30"]
    - ["Rom 1:16", "Rom 10:14-17", "Eph 5:26"]
    - ["Acts 2:42-47", "Eph 4:1-6"]
    - ["Rom 8:29", "Eph 1:3-14"]
    - ["1 Jn 3:14", "1 Jn 3:19-21"]
    - ["Ps 23:6", "Jn 10:27-28", "1 Cor 1:4-9", "1 Pet 1:3-5"]

q-55:
  question: "What do you understand by the communion of saints?"
  answer:
    - "First, that believers, all and everyone, as members of Christ have communion with him and share in all his treasures and gifts. ^1"
    - "Second, that everyone is duty-bound to use his gifts readily and cheerfully for the benefit and well-being of the other members. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Rom 8:32", "1 Cor 6:17", "1 Cor 12:4-7", "1 Cor 12:12-13", "1 Jn 1:3"]
    - ["Rom 12:4-8", "1 Cor 12:20-27", "1 Cor 13:1-7", "Phil 2:4-8"]

q-56:
  question: "What do you believe concerning the forgiveness of sins?"
  answer:
    - "I believe that God, because of Christ's satisfaction, will no more remember my sins, ^1 nor my sinful nature, against which I have to struggle all my life, ^2 but will graciously grant me the righteousness of Christ, that I may never come into condemnation. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Ps 103:3-4", "Ps 103:10", "Ps 103:12", "Mic 7:18-19", "2 Cor 5:18-21", "1 Jn 1:7", "1 Jn 2:2"]
    - ["Rom 7:21-25"]
    - ["Jn 3:17-18", "Jn 5:24", "Rom 8:1-2"]

q-57:
  question: "What comfort does the resurrection of the body offer you?"
  answer:
    - "Not only shall my soul after this life immediately be taken up to Christ, my Head, ^1 but also this my flesh, raised by the power of Christ, shall be reunited with my soul and made like Christ's glorious body. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Lk 16:22", "Lk 23:43", "Phil 1:21-23"]
    - ["Job 19:25-26", "1 Cor 15:20", "1 Cor 15:42-46", "1 Cor 15:54", "Phil 3:21", "1 Jn 3:2"]

q-58:
  question: "What comfort do you receive from the article about the life everlasting?"
  answer:
    - "Since I now already feel in my heart the beginning of eternal joy, ^1 I shall after this life possess perfect blessedness, such as no eye has seen, nor ear heard, nor the heart of man conceived – a blessedness in which to praise God forever. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Jn 17:3", "Rom 14:17", "2 Cor 5:2-3"]
    - ["Jn 17:24", "1 Cor 2:9"]

q-59:
  question: "But what does it help you now that you believe all this?"
  answer:
    - "In Christ I am righteous before God and heir to life everlasting. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Hab 2:4", "Jn 3:36", "Rom 1:17", "Rom 5:1-2"]

q-60:
  question: "How are you righteous before God?"
  answer:
    - "Only by true faith in Jesus Christ. ^1 Although my conscience accuses me that I have grievously sinned against all God's commandments, have never kept any of them, ^2 and am still inclined to all evil, ^3 yet God, without any merit of my own, ^4 imputes to me the perfect satisfaction, righteousness, and holiness of Christ. ^5 He grants these to me as if I had never had nor committed any sin, and as if I myself had accomplished all the obedience which Christ has rendered for me, ^6 if only I accept this gift with a believing heart. ^7"
  refs:
    - ["Rom 3:21-28", "Gal 2:16", "Eph 2:8-9", "Phil 3:8-11"]
    - ["Rom 3:9-10"]
    - ["Rom 7:23"]
    - ["Deut 9:6", "Ezek 36:22", "Tit 3:4-5"]
    - ["Rom 3:24", "Eph 2:8"]
    - ["Rom 4:3-5", "2 Cor 5:17-19", "1 Jn 2:1-2"]
    - ["Rom 4:24-25", "2 Cor 5:21"]

q-61:
  question: "Why do you say that you are righteous only by faith?"
  answer:
    - "Not that I am acceptable to God on account of the worthiness of my faith, for only the satisfaction, righteousness, and holiness of Christ is my righteousness before God. ^1 I can receive this righteousness and make it my own by faith only. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["1 Cor 1:30-31", "1 Cor 2:2"]
    - ["Rom 10:10", "1 Jn 5:10-12"]

q-62:
  question: "But why can our good works not be our righteousness before God, or at least a part of it?"
  answer:
    - "Because the righteousness which can stand before God's judgment must be absolutely perfect and in complete agreement with the law of God. ^1 Whereas even our best works in this life are all imperfect and defiled with sin. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Deut 27:26", "Gal 3:10"]
    - ["Is 64:6"]

q-63:
  question: "But do our good works earn nothing, even though God promises to reward them in this life and the next? ^1"
  answer:
    - "This reward is not earned; it is a gift of grace. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 5:12", "Heb 11:6"]
    - ["Lk 17:10", "2 Tim 4:7-8"]

q-64:
  question: "Does this teaching not make people careless and wicked?"
  answer:
    - "No. It is impossible that those grafted into Christ by true faith should not bring forth fruits of thankfulness. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 7:18", "Lk 6:43-45", "Jn 15:5"]

q-65:
  question: "Since then faith alone makes us share in Christ and all his benefits, where does this faith come from?"
  answer:
    - "From the Holy Spirit, ^1 who works it in our hearts by the preaching of the gospel, ^2 and strengthens it by the use of the sacraments. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Jn 3:5", "1 Cor 2:10-14", "Eph 2:8", "Phil 1:29"]
    - ["Rom 10:17", "1 Pet 1:23-25"]
    - ["Mt 28:19-20", "1 Cor 10:16"]

q-66:
  question: "What are the sacraments?"
  answer:
    - "The sacraments are holy, visible signs and seals. They were instituted by God so that by their use he might the more fully declare and seal to us the promise of the gospel. ^1"
    - "And this is the promise: that God graciously grants us forgiveness of sins and everlasting life because of the one sacrifice of Christ accomplished on the cross. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Gen 17:11", "Deut 30:6", "Rom 4:11"]
    - ["Mt 26:27-28", "Acts 2:38", "Heb 10:10"]

q-67:
  question: "Are both the Word and the sacraments then intended to focus our faith on the sacrifice of Jesus Christ on the cross as the only ground of our salvation?"
  answer:
    - "Yes, indeed. The Holy Spirit teaches us in the gospel and assures us by the sacraments that our entire salvation rests on Christ's one sacrifice for us on the cross. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Rom 6:3", "1 Cor 11:26", "Gal 3:27"]

q-68:
  question: "How many sacraments has Christ instituted in the new covenant?"
  answer:
    - "Two: holy baptism and the holy supper. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 28:19-20", "1 Cor 11:23-26"]

q-69:
  question: "How does holy baptism signify and seal to you that the one sacrifice of Christ on the cross benefits you?"
  answer:
    - "In this way: Christ instituted this outward washing ^1 and with it gave the promise that, as surely as water washes away the dirt from the body, so certainly his blood and Spirit wash away the impurity of my soul, that is, all my sins. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 28:19"]
    - ["Mt 3:11", "Mk 16:16", "Jn 1:33", "Acts 2:38", "Rom 6:3-4", "1 Pet 3:21"]

q-70:
  question: "What does it mean to be washed with Christ's blood and Spirit?"
  answer:
    - "To be washed with Christ's blood means to receive forgiveness of sins from God, through grace, because of Christ's blood, poured out for us in his sacrifice on the cross. ^1 To be washed with his Spirit means to be renewed by the Holy Spirit and sanctified to be members of Christ, so that more and more we become dead to sin and lead a holy and blameless life. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Ezek 36:25", "Zech 13:1", "Eph 1:7", "Heb 12:24", "1 Pet 1:2", "Rev 1:5", "Rev 7:14"]
    - ["Jn 3:5-8", "Rom 6:4", "1 Cor 6:11", "Col 2:11-12"]

q-71:
  question: "Where has Christ promised that he will wash us with his blood and Spirit as surely as we are washed with the water of baptism?"
  answer:
    - "In the institution of baptism, where he says: Therefore go and make disciples of all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit (Mt 28:19). Whoever believes and is baptized will be saved, but whoever does not believe will be condemned (Mk 16:16). This promise is repeated where Scripture calls baptism the washing of rebirth and the washing away of sins (Titus 3:5; Acts 22:16)."
  refs: []

q-72:
  question: "Does this outward washing with water itself wash away sins?"
  answer:
    - "No, only the blood of Jesus Christ and the Holy Spirit cleanse us from all sins. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 3:11", "1 Pet 3:21", "1 Jn 1:7"]

q-73:
  question: "Why then does the Holy Spirit call baptism the washing of regeneration and the washing away of sins?"
  answer:
    - "God speaks in this way for a good reason. He wants to teach us that the blood and Spirit of Christ remove our sins just as water takes away dirt from the body. ^1 But, even more important, he wants to assure us by this divine pledge and sign that we are as truly cleansed from our sins spiritually as we are bodily washed with water. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["1 Cor 6:11", "Rev 1:5", "Rev 7:14"]
    - ["Mk 16:16", "Acts 2:38", "Rom 6:3-4", "Gal 3:27"]

q-74:
  question: "Should infants, too, be baptized?"
  answer:
    - "Yes. Infants as well as adults belong to God's covenant and congregation. ^1 Through Christ's blood the redemption from sin and the Holy Spirit, who works faith, are promised to them no less than to adults. ^2"
    - "Therefore, by baptism, as sign of the covenant, they must be incorporated into the Christian church and distinguished from the children of unbelievers. ^3"
    - "This was done in the old covenant by circumcision, ^4 in place of which baptism was instituted in the new covenant. ^5"
  refs:
    - ["Gen 17:7", "Mt 19:14"]
    - ["Ps 22:10", "Is 44:1-3", "Acts 2:38-39", "Acts 16:31"]
    - ["Acts 10:47", "1 Cor 7:14"]
    - ["Gen 17:9-14"]
    - ["Col 2:11-13"]

q-75:
  question: "How does the Lord's supper signify and seal to you that you share in Christ's one sacrifice on the cross and in all his gifts?"
  answer:
    - "In this way:"
    - "Christ has commanded me and all believers to eat of this broken bread and drink of this cup in remembrance of him."
    - "With this command he gave these promises: ^1"
    - "First, as surely as I see with my eyes the bread of the Lord broken for me and the cup given to me, so surely was his body offered for me and his blood poured out for me on the cross."
    - "Second, as surely as I receive from the hand of the minister and taste with my mouth the bread and the cup of the Lord as sure signs of Christ's body and blood, so surely does he himself nourish and refresh my soul to everlasting life with his crucified body and shed blood."
  refs:
    - ["Mt 26:26-28", "Mk 14:22-24", "Lk 22:19-20", "1 Cor 11:23-25"]

q-76:
  question: "What does it mean to eat the crucified body of Christ and to drink his shed blood?"
  answer:
    - "First, to accept with a believing heart all the suffering and the death of Christ, and so receive forgiveness of sins and life eternal. ^1"
    - "Second, to be united more and more to his sacred body through the Holy Spirit, who lives both in Christ and in us. ^2"
    - "Therefore, although Christ is in heaven ^3 and we are on earth, yet we are flesh of his flesh and bone of his bones, ^4 and we forever live and are governed by one Spirit, as the members of our body are by one soul. ^5"
  refs:
    - ["Jn 6:35", "Jn 6:40", "Jn 6:50-54"]
    - ["Jn 6:55-56", "1 Cor 12:13"]
    - ["Acts 1:9-11", "Acts 3:21", "1 Cor 11:26", "Col 3:1"]
    - ["1 Cor 6:15", "1 Cor 6:17", "Eph 5:29-30", "1 Jn 4:13"]
    - ["Jn 6:56-58", "Jn 15:1-6", "Eph 4:15-16", "1 Jn 3:24"]

q-77:
  question: "Where has Christ promised that he will nourish and refresh believers with his body and blood as surely as they eat of this broken bread and drink of this cup?"
  answer:
    - "In the institution of the Lord's supper:"
    - "The Lord Jesus, on the night he was betrayed, took bread, and when he had given thanks, he broke it and said,"
    - "\"This is my body, which is for you; do this in remembrance of me.\""
    - "In the same way, after supper he took the cup, saying,"
    - "\"This cup is the new covenant in my blood; do this, whenever you drink it, in remembrance of me.\""
    - "For whenever you eat this bread and drink this cup, you proclaim the Lord's death until he comes). ^1"
    - "This promise is repeated by Paul where he says:"
    - "Is not the cup of thanksgiving for which we give thanks a participation in the blood of Christ?"
    - "And is not the bread that we break a participation in the body of Christ?"
    - "Because there is one loaf, we, who are many, are one body, for we all partake of the one loaf. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["1 Cor 11:23-26"]
    - ["1 Cor 10:16-17"]

q-78:
  question: "Are then the bread and wine changed into the real body and blood of Christ?"
  answer:
    - "No."
    - "Just as the water of baptism is not changed into the blood of Christ and is not the washing away of sins itself but is simply God's sign and pledge, ^1 so also the bread in the Lord's supper does not become the body of Christ itself, ^2 although it is called Christ's body ^3 in keeping with the nature and usage of sacraments. ^4"
  refs:
    - ["Eph 5:26", "Tit 3:5"]
    - ["Mt 26:26-29"]
    - ["1 Cor 10:16-17", "1 Cor 11:26-28"]
    - ["Gen 17:10-11", "Ex 12:11", "Ex 12:13", "1 Cor 10:3-4", "1 Pet 3:21"]

q-79:
  question: "Why then does Christ call the bread his body and the cup his blood, or the new covenant in his blood, and why does Paul speak of a participation in the body and blood of Christ?"
  answer:
    - "Christ speaks in this way for a good reason: He wants to teach us by his supper that as bread and wine sustain us in this temporal life, so his crucified body and shed blood are true food and drink for our souls to eternal life. ^1"
    - "But, even more important, he wants to assure us by this visible sign and pledge, first, that through the working of the Holy Spirit we share in his true body and blood as surely as we receive with our mouth these holy signs in remembrance of him, ^2 and, second, that all his suffering and obedience are as certainly ours as if we personally had suffered and paid for our sins. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Jn 6:51", "Jn 6:55"]
    - ["1 Cor 10:16-17", "1 Cor 11:26"]
    - ["Rom 6:5-11"]

q-80:
  question: "What difference is there between the Lord's supper and the papal mass?"
  answer:
    - "The Lord's supper testifies to us, first, that we have complete forgiveness of all our sins through the one sacrifice of Jesus Christ, which he himself accomplished on the cross once for all; ^1 and, second, that through the Holy Spirit we are grafted into Christ, ^2 who with his true body is now in heaven at the right hand of the Father, ^3 and this is where he wants to be worshipped. ^4"
    - "But the mass teaches, first, that the living and the dead do not have forgiveness of sins through the suffering of Christ unless he is still offered for them daily by the priests; and, second, that Christ is bodily present in the form of bread and wine, and there is to be worshipped."
    - "Therefore the mass is basically nothing but a denial of the one sacrifice and suffering of Jesus Christ, and an accursed idolatry."
  refs:
    - ["Mt 26:28", "Jn 19:30", "Heb 7:27", "Heb 9:12", "Heb 9:25-26", "Heb 10:10-18"]
    - ["1 Cor 6:17", "1 Cor 10:16-17"]
    - ["Jn 20:17", "Acts 7:55-56", "Heb 1:3", "Heb 8:1"]
    - ["Jn 4:21-24", "Phil 3:20", "Col 3:1", "1 Thess 1:10"]

q-81:
  question: "Who are to come to the table of the Lord?"
  answer:
    - "Those who are truly displeased with themselves because of their sins and yet trust that these are forgiven them and that their remaining weakness is covered by the suffering and death of Christ, and who also desire more and more to strengthen their faith and amend their life."
    - "But hypocrites and those who do not repent eat and drink judgment upon themselves. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["1 Cor 10:19-22", "1 Cor 11:26-32"]

q-82:
  question: "Are those also to be admitted to the Lord's supper who by their confession and life show that they are unbelieving and ungodly?"
  answer:
    - "No, for then the covenant of God would be profaned and his wrath kindled against the whole congregation. ^1"
    - "Therefore, according to the command of Christ and his apostles, the Christian church is duty-bound to exclude such persons by the keys of the kingdom of heaven, until they amend their lives."
  refs:
    - ["Ps 50:16", "Is 1:11-17", "1 Cor 11:17-34"]

q-83:
  question: "What are the keys of the kingdom of heaven?"
  answer:
    - "The preaching of the holy gospel and church discipline."
    - "By these two the kingdom of heaven is opened to believers and closed to unbelievers. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 16:19", "Jn 20:21-23"]

q-84:
  question: "How is the kingdom of heaven opened and closed by the preaching of the gospel?"
  answer:
    - "According to the command of Christ, the kingdom of heaven is opened when it is proclaimed and publicly testified to each and every believer that God has really forgiven all their sins for the sake of Christ's merits, as often as they by true faith accept the promise of the gospel."
    - "The kingdom of heaven is closed when it is proclaimed and testified to all unbelievers and hypocrites that the wrath of God and eternal condemnation rest on them as long as they do not repent."
    - "According to this testimony of the gospel, God will judge both in this life and in the life to come. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 16:19", "Jn 3:31-36", "Jn 20:21-23"]

q-85:
  question: "How is the kingdom of heaven closed and opened by church discipline?"
  answer:
    - "According to the command of Christ, people who call themselves Christians but show themselves to be un-christian in doctrine or life are first repeatedly admonished in a brotherly manner."
    - "If they do not give up their errors or wickedness, they are reported to the church, that is, to the elders."
    - "If they do not heed also their admonitions, they are forbidden the use of the sacraments, and they are excluded by the elders from the Christian congregation, and by God himself from the kingdom of Christ. ^1"
    - "They are again received as members of Christ and of the church when they promise and show real amendment. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 18:15-20", "1 Cor 5:3-5", "1 Cor 5:11-13", "2 Thess 3:14-15"]
    - ["Lk 15:20-24", "2 Cor 2:6-11"]

q-86:
  question: "Since we have been delivered from our misery by grace alone through Christ, without any merit of our own, why must we yet do good works?"
  answer:
    - "Because Christ, having redeemed us by his blood, also renews us by his Holy Spirit to be his image, so that with our whole life we may show ourselves thankful to God for his benefits, ^1 and he may be praised by us. ^2"
    - "Further, that we ourselves may be assured of our faith by its fruits, ^3 and that by our godly walk of life we may win our neighbours for Christ. ^4"
  refs:
    - ["Rom 6:13", "Rom 12:1-2", "1 Pet 2:5-10"]
    - ["Mt 5:16", "1 Cor 6:19-20"]
    - ["Mt 7:17-18", "Gal 5:22-24", "2 Pet 1:10-11"]
    - ["Mt 5:14-16", "Rom 14:17-19", "1 Pet 2:12", "1 Pet 3:1-2"]

q-87:
  question: "Can those be saved who do not turn to God from their ungrateful and impenitent walk of life?"
  answer:
    - "By no means. Scripture says that no unchaste person, idolater, adulterer, thief, greedy person, drunkard, slanderer, robber, or the like shall inherit the kingdom of God. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["1 Cor 6:9-10", "Gal 5:19-21", "Eph 5:5-6", "1 Jn 3:14"]

q-88:
  question: "What is the true repentance or conversion of man?"
  answer:
    - "It is the dying of the old nature and the coming to life of the new. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Rom 6:1-11", "1 Cor 5:7", "2 Cor 5:17", "Eph 4:22-24", "Col 3:5-10"]

q-89:
  question: "What is the dying of the old nature?"
  answer:
    - "It is to grieve with heartfelt sorrow that we have offended God by our sin, and more and more to hate it and flee from it. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Ps 51:3-4", "Ps 51:17", "Joel 2:12-13", "Rom 8:12-13", "2 Cor 7:10"]

q-90:
  question: "What is the coming to life of the new nature?"
  answer:
    - "It is a heartfelt joy in God through Christ, ^1 and a love and delight to live according to the will of God in all good works. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Ps 51:8", "Ps 51:12", "Is 57:15", "Rom 5:1", "Rom 14:17"]
    - ["Rom 6:10-11", "Gal 2:20"]

q-91:
  question: "But what are good works?"
  answer:
    - "Only those which are done out of true faith, ^1 in accordance with the law of God, ^2 and to his glory, ^3 and not those based on our own opinion or on precepts of men. ^4"
  refs:
    - ["Jn 15:5", "Rom 14:23", "Heb 11:6"]
    - ["Lev 18:4", "1 Sam 15:22", "Eph 2:10"]
    - ["1 Cor 10:31"]
    - ["Deut 12:32", "Is 29:13", "Ezek 20:18-19", "Mt 15:7-9"]

q-92:
  question: "What is the law of the LORD?"
  answer:
    - "God spoke all these words:"
    - "I am the LORD your God, who brought you out of Egypt, out of the land of slavery."
    - "1. You shall have no other gods before me."
    - "2. You shall not make for yourself an idol in the form of anything in heaven above or on the earth beneath or in the waters below. You shall not bow down to them or worship them; for I, the LORD your God, am a jealous God, punishing the children for the sin of the fathers to the third and fourth generation of those who hate me, but showing love to a thousand generations of those who love me and keep my commandments."
    - "3. You shall not misuse the name of the LORD your God, for the LORD will not hold anyone guiltless who misuses his name."
    - "4. Remember the Sabbath day by keeping it holy. Six days you shall labor and do all your work, but the seventh day is a Sabbath to the LORD your God. On it you shall not do any work, neither you, nor your son or daughter, nor your manservant or maidservant, nor your animals, nor the alien within your gates. For in six days the LORD made the heavens and the earth, the sea, and all that is in them, but he rested on the seventh day. Therefore the LORD blessed the Sabbath day and made it holy."
    - "5. Honor your father and your mother, so that you may live long in the land the LORD your God is giving you."
    - "6. You shall not murder."
    - "7. You shall not commit adultery."
    - "8. You shall not steal."
    - "9. You shall not give false testimony against your neighbor."
    - "10. You shall not covet your neighbor's house. You shall not covet your neighbor's wife, or his manservant or maidservant, his ox or donkey, or anything that belongs to your neighbor. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Ex 20:1-17", "Deut 5:6-21"]

q-93:
  question: "How are these commandments divided?"
  answer:
    - "Into two parts."
    - "The first teaches us how to live in relation to God; the second, what duties we owe our neighbour. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 22:37-40"]

q-94:
  question: "What does the LORD require in the first commandment?"
  answer:
    - "That for the sake of my very salvation I avoid and flee all idolatry, ^1 witchcraft, superstition, ^2 and prayer to saints or to other creatures. ^3"
    - "Further, that I rightly come to know the only true God, ^4 trust in him alone, ^5 submit to him with all humility ^6 and patience, ^7 expect all good from him only, ^8 and love, ^9 fear, ^10 and honour him ^11 with all my heart."
    - "In short, that I forsake all creatures rather than do the least thing against his will. ^12"
  refs:
    - ["1 Cor 6:9-10", "1 Cor 10:5-14", "1 Jn 5:21"]
    - ["Lev 19:31", "Deut 18:9-12"]
    - ["Mt 4:10", "Rev 19:10", "Rev 22:8-9"]
    - ["Jn 17:3"]
    - ["Jer 17:5", "Jer 17:7"]
    - ["1 Pet 5:5-6"]
    - ["Rom 5:3-4", "1 Cor 10:10", "Phil 2:14", "Col 1:11", "Heb 10:36"]
    - ["Ps 104:27-28", "Is 45:7", "Jas 1:17"]
    - ["Deut 6:5", "Mt 22:37"]
    - ["Deut 6:2", "Ps 111:10", "Prov 1:7", "Prov 9:10", "Mt 10:28", "1 Pet 1:17"]
    - ["Deut 6:13", "Mt 4:10", "Deut 10:20"]
    - ["Mt 5:29-30", "Mt 10:37-39", "Acts 5:29"]

q-95:
  question: "What is idolatry?"
  answer:
    - "Idolatry is having or inventing something in which to put our trust instead of, or in addition to, the only true God who has revealed himself in his Word. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["1 Chron 16:26", "Gal 4:8-9", "Eph 5:5", "Phil 3:19"]

q-96:
  question: "What does God require in the second commandment?"
  answer:
    - "We are not to make an image of God in any way, ^1 nor to worship him in any other manner than he has commanded in his Word. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Deut 4:15-19", "Is 40:18-25", "Acts 17:29", "Rom 1:23"]
    - ["Lev 10:1-7", "Deut 12:30", "1 Sam 15:22-23", "Mt 15:9", "Jn 4:23-24"]

q-97:
  question: "May we then not make any image at all?"
  answer:
    - "God cannot and may not be visibly portrayed in any way. Creatures may be portrayed, but God forbids us to make or have any images of them in order to worship them or to serve God through them. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Ex 34:13-14", "Ex 34:17", "Num 33:52", "2 Kings 18:4-5", "Is 40:25"]

q-98:
  question: "But may images not be tolerated in the churches as \"books for the laity\"?"
  answer:
    - "No, for we should not be wiser than God. He wants his people to be taught not by means of dumb images ^1 but by the living preaching of his Word. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Jer 10:8", "Hab 2:18-20"]
    - ["Rom 10:14-15", "Rom 10:17", "2 Tim 3:16-17", "2 Pet 1:19"]

q-99:
  question: "What is required in the third commandment?"
  answer:
    - "We are not to blaspheme or to abuse the name of God by cursing, ^1 perjury, ^2 or unnecessary oaths, ^3 nor to share in such horrible sins by being silent bystanders. ^4 Rather, we must use the holy name of God only with fear and reverence, ^5 so that we may rightly confess him, ^6 call upon him, ^7 and praise him in all our words and works. ^8"
  refs:
    - ["Lev 24:10-17"]
    - ["Lev 19:12"]
    - ["Mt 5:37", "Jas 5:12"]
    - ["Lev 5:1", "Prov 29:24"]
    - ["Ps 99:1-5", "Is 45:23", "Jer 4:2"]
    - ["Mt 10:32-33", "Rom 10:9-10"]
    - ["Ps 50:14-15", "1 Tim 2:8"]
    - ["Rom 2:24", "Col 3:17", "1 Tim 6:1"]

q-100:
  question: "Is the blaspheming of God's name by swearing and cursing such a grievous sin that God is angry also with those who do not prevent and forbid it as much as they can?"
  answer:
    - "Certainly, ^1 for no sin is greater or provokes God's wrath more than the blaspheming of his name. That is why he commanded it to be punished with death. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Lev 5:1"]
    - ["Lev 24:16"]

q-101:
  question: "But may we swear an oath by the name of God in a godly manner?"
  answer:
    - "Yes, when the government demands it of its subjects, or when necessity requires it, in order to maintain and promote fidelity and truth, to God's glory and for our neighbour's good. Such oath-taking is based on God's Word ^1 and was therefore rightly used by saints in the Old and the New Testament. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Deut 6:13", "Deut 10:20", "Jer 4:1-2", "Heb 6:16"]
    - ["Gen 21:24", "Gen 31:53", "Josh 9:15", "1 Sam 24:22", "1 Kings 1:29-30", "Rom 1:9", "2 Cor 1:23"]

q-102:
  question: "May we also swear by saints or other creatures?"
  answer:
    - "No."
    - "A lawful oath is a calling upon God, who alone knows the heart, to bear witness to the truth, and to punish me if I swear falsely. ^1 No creature is worthy of such honour. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Rom 9:1", "2 Cor 1:23"]
    - ["Mt 5:34-37", "Mt 23:16-22", "Jas 5:12"]

q-103:
  question: "What does God require in the fourth commandment?"
  answer:
    - "First, that the ministry of the gospel and the schools be maintained ^1 and that, especially on the day of rest, I diligently attend the church of God ^2 to hear God's Word, ^3 to use the sacraments, ^4 to call publicly upon the LORD, ^5 and to give Christian offerings for the poor. ^6"
    - "Second, that all the days of my life I rest from my evil works, let the LORD work in me through his Holy Spirit, and so begin in this life the eternal Sabbath. ^7"
  refs:
    - ["Deut 6:4-9", "Deut 20:25", "1 Cor 9:13-14", "2 Tim 2:2", "2 Tim 3:13-17", "Tit 1:5"]
    - ["Deut 12:5-12", "Ps 40:9-10", "Ps 68:26", "Acts 2:42-47", "Heb 10:23-25"]
    - ["Rom 10:14-17", "1 Cor 14:26-33", "1 Tim 4:13"]
    - ["1 Cor 11:23-24"]
    - ["Col 3:16", "1 Tim 2:1"]
    - ["Ps 50:14", "1 Cor 16:2", "2 Cor 8-9"]
    - ["Is 66:23", "Heb 4:9-11"]

q-104:
  question: "What does God require in the fifth commandment?"
  answer:
    - "That I show all honour, love, and faithfulness to my father and mother and to all those in authority over me, submit myself with due obedience to their good instruction and discipline, ^1 and also have patience with their weaknesses and shortcomings, ^2 since it is God's will to govern us by their hand. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Ex 21:17", "Prov 1:8", "Prov 4:1", "Rom 13:1-2", "Eph 5:21-22", "Eph 6:1-9", "Col 3:18-25"]
    - ["Prov 20:20", "Prov 23:22", "1 Pet 2:18"]
    - ["Mt 22:21", "Rom 13:1-8", "Eph 6:1-9", "Col 3:18-21"]

q-105:
  question: "What does God require in the sixth commandment?"
  answer:
    - "I am not to dishonour, hate, injure, or kill my neighbour by thoughts, words, or gestures, and much less by deeds, whether personally or through another; ^1 rather, I am to put away all desire of revenge. ^2 Moreover, I am not to harm or recklessly endanger myself. ^3 Therefore, also, the government bears the sword to prevent murder. ^4"
  refs:
    - ["Gen 9:6", "Lev 19:17-18", "Mt 5:21-22", "Mt 26:52"]
    - ["Prov 25:21-22", "Mt 18:35", "Rom 12:19", "Eph 4:26"]
    - ["Mt 5:21-22"]
    - ["Rom 13:4"]

q-106:
  question: "Does this commandment speak only of killing with the sword?"
  answer:
    - "No."
    - "By forbidding murder God teaches us that he abhors the root of murder, such as envy, hatred, anger, and desire for revenge, and that he regards all these as hidden murder. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Gen 4:8", "Mt 5:21-22", "1 Jn 3:15"]

q-107:
  question: "Is it enough then that we do not kill our neighbour in any such way?"
  answer:
    - "No."
    - "When our neighbours are in danger of body or soul, we must protect them from harm and promote their good. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Is 58:6-7", "Mt 25:35-40", "Gal 6:2", "Phil 2:4"]

q-108:
  question: "What does the seventh commandment teach us?"
  answer:
    - "That God condemns all unchastity, ^1 and that therefore we should loathe it with all our heart ^2 and live decent and chaste lives, within or outside of the holy state of marriage. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Lev 18:30", "Deut 22:25-27", "1 Cor 6:18"]
    - ["Jude 23"]
    - ["1 Cor 7:1-9", "Heb 13:4"]

q-109:
  question: "Does God in this commandment forbid only such scandalous sins as adultery?"
  answer:
    - "We are to restrain the unchaste thoughts and desires of our hearts ^1 and not allow them to move us to impure actions, ^2 looks, ^3 words, ^4 jokes, ^5 or the lustful longing of the body. ^6"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 5:27-28"]
    - ["Eph 5:3-5"]
    - ["1 Cor 6:18"]
    - ["Eph 5:4", "Col 3:8"]
    - ["Eph 5:4"]
    - ["1 Cor 6:18-20"]

q-110:
  question: "What does God forbid in the eighth commandment?"
  answer:
    - "He forbids not only outright theft ^1 and robbery, punishable by the government. ^2 But God also forbids all scheming and swindling in order to get our neighbour's goods for ourselves, whether by force or by appearance of right, such as unjust weights, lengths, measures, deceptive advertising, false measures, excessive interest, or any other means forbidden by God. ^3 In addition he forbids all greed ^4 and pointless squandering of his gifts. ^5"
  refs:
    - ["Ex 22:1-4", "Lev 19:11-13"]
    - ["Ps 62:10"]
    - ["Deut 25:13-16", "Prov 11:1", "Prov 16:11", "Ezek 45:9-10", "Amos 8:4-6", "Mic 6:9-12", "Lk 3:14", "1 Thess 4:6"]
    - ["Lk 12:15"]
    - ["Prov 21:20", "Prov 23:20-21", "Lk 15:13"]

q-111:
  question: "But what does God require of you in this commandment?"
  answer:
    - "I must promote my neighbour's good wherever I can and may, deal with him as I would like others to deal with me, and work faithfully so that I may share with those in need. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Is 58:10", "Gal 6:10", "Eph 4:28", "1 Tim 6:17-18", "Heb 13:16"]

q-112:
  question: "What is required in the ninth commandment?"
  answer:
    - "I must promote my neighbour's good name and speak well of him, ^1 defend and protect him, ^2 and promote his honour and well-being as I would my own. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["1 Pet 4:8"]
    - ["Prov 31:8-9"]
    - ["1 Cor 13:7", "Phil 2:4"]

q-113:
  question: "What is required in the tenth commandment?"
  answer:
    - "That not even the least inclination or thought against any commandment of God ever enter my heart. ^1 Rather, with all my heart I must always love God and my neighbour. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Jer 17:9", "Rom 7:7-8", "Jas 1:14-15"]
    - ["Mt 22:37-39", "Rom 13:9-10"]

q-114:
  question: "But can those who are converted to God obey the ten commandments perfectly?"
  answer:
    - "No. In this life even the holiest have only a small beginning of this obedience. ^1 Nevertheless, they begin with serious purpose to live not according to some, but all the commandments of God. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Eccl 7:20", "Rom 7:14-25", "1 Jn 1:8-10"]
    - ["Ps 1:1-2", "Rom 7:22-23"]

q-115:
  question: "Why then does God make the ten commandments known to the believers if in this life they cannot obey them perfectly?"
  answer:
    - "First, that throughout our life we may more and more come to know our sinful nature ^1 and thus be moved to pray more earnestly for the forgiveness of sins and for righteousness in Christ. ^2"
    - "Second, that we may ceaselessly strive and beg God for the grace of the Holy Spirit, so that more and more we are renewed in the image of God, until after this life we reach the goal of perfection. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Ps 32:5", "Rom 3:19-20", "Rom 7:23-25", "1 Jn 1:9"]
    - ["Ps 51:1-2", "Ps 51:12"]
    - ["1 Cor 13:9-10", "Phil 3:12-14", "1 Jn 3:1-3"]

q-116:
  question: "Why is prayer necessary for a Christian?"
  answer:
    - "Because it is the chief part of the thankfulness which God requires of us, ^1 and because God will give his grace and Holy Spirit only to those who earnestly and without ceasing ask them of him and thank him for them. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Ps 50:14-15", "Ps 116:12-19", "1 Thess 5:17-18"]
    - ["Mt 7:7-8", "Lk 11:9-13"]

q-117:
  question: "What belongs to a prayer which pleases God and is heard by him?"
  answer:
    - "First, that with heart-felt longing ^1 we pray to the one true God only, ^2 for all that he has commanded us to pray for. ^3"
    - "Second, that we earnestly ask of the Lord ^4 what he has promised in his Word. ^5"
    - "Third, that we present our prayers with true faith, ^6 so that we receive what he has promised. ^7"
  refs:
    - ["Ps 145:18-19", "Rom 10:13-14"]
    - ["Deut 6:4-5", "Jn 4:22-24"]
    - ["Mt 6:9-13", "Lk 11:2-4"]
    - ["Rom 8:26"]
    - ["2 Sam 7:28", "Ps 143:1", "Mt 7:7-8", "Lk 11:9-13"]
    - ["Jas 1:6"]
    - ["Mt 21:22", "Jas 1:6", "1 Jn 5:14-15"]

q-118:
  question: "What has God commanded us to pray for?"
  answer:
    - "All things we need, ^1 spiritually and physically, ^2 as embraced in the prayer Christ our Lord himself taught us. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 6:33", "Jas 1:5"]
    - ["Mt 6:11", "Lk 12:22"]
    - ["Mt 6:9-13", "Lk 11:2-4"]

q-119:
  question: "What is the prayer?"
  answer:
    - "Our Father in heaven, hallowed be your name, your kingdom come, your will be done on earth as it is in heaven. Give us today our daily bread. Forgive us our debts, as we also have forgiven our debtors. And lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one. For yours is the kingdom and the power and the glory forever. Amen. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 6:9-13", "Lk 11:2-4"]

q-120:
  question: "Why has Christ commanded us to address God thus: 'Our Father'?"
  answer:
    - "That immediately, at the very beginning of our prayer, he might arouse in us childlike reverence and trust toward God, ^1 who is not to be approached with dread or terror, but with childlike confidence and love, as children approach an affectionate father. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Jer 31:9", "Mt 6:9"]
    - ["Mt 7:9-11", "Lk 11:11-13"]

q-121:
  question: "Why is the word 'our' added?"
  answer:
    - "That immediately, at the very beginning of our prayer, he might arouse in us childlike reverence and trust toward God, who is not to be approached with dread or terror, but with childlike confidence and love, as children approach an affectionate father. ^1"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 6:9"]

q-122:
  question: "What is the first petition?"
  answer:
    - "Hallowed be your name, that is: Grant us first of all that we may rightly know you, ^1 and hallow, glorify, praise, and adore you in all your works and in all your ways, ^2 that we may never blaspheme you, ^3 but may confess, honour, and praise you all our life. ^4"
  refs:
    - ["Ps 119:105", "Jer 9:23-24", "Jn 17:3", "Hos 6:3"]
    - ["Ex 34:5-8", "Ps 145", "Ps 145:1-21"]
    - ["Ps 115:1", "Mt 5:16"]
    - ["Ps 71:8"]

q-123:
  question: "What is the second petition?"
  answer:
    - "Your kingdom come, that is: So govern us by your Word and Spirit that more and more we submit ourselves to you. ^1 Preserve and increase your church. ^2 Destroy every force which revolts against you and every conspiracy against your Word. ^3 Do this until the fulness of your kingdom comes, when you will be all in all. ^4"
  refs:
    - ["Ps 119:5", "Ps 143:10", "Mt 6:33"]
    - ["Ps 122:9", "Mt 16:18", "Jn 10:16"]
    - ["Ps 2:8-9", "Rom 16:20", "1 Jn 3:8"]
    - ["1 Cor 15:28", "Rev 22:20"]

q-124:
  question: "What is the third petition?"
  answer:
    - "Your will be done on earth as it is in heaven, that is: Grant that we and all men may deny our own will ^1 and obey your will without any murmuring, ^2 as the angels do in heaven. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 16:24", "Tit 2:11-12"]
    - ["Ps 103:20-21", "Lk 22:42"]
    - ["Ps 103:20-21"]

q-125:
  question: "What is the fourth petition?"
  answer:
    - "Give us today our daily bread, that is: Provide for us day by day all that we need for body and soul, ^1 and grant that we may recognize that you are the only source of all good, ^2 and that we may thank you and trust in you completely. ^3"
  refs:
    - ["Mt 6:11", "Lk 11:3", "Jas 1:17"]
    - ["Ps 104:27-30", "Ps 145:15-16", "Mt 6:25-34"]
    - ["Ps 62:8", "Ps 104:27-30", "Mt 6:25-34"]

q-126:
  question: "What is the fifth petition?"
  answer:
    - "Forgive us our debts, as we also have forgiven our debtors, that is: For the sake of Christ's blood, do not charge to us, poor sinners, any of the sins we do or the evil which constantly clings to us. ^1 Grant also that we may wholeheartedly forgive others and never hold their sins against them. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["Ps 51:1-4", "Ps 143:2", "1 Jn 2:1-2"]
    - ["Mt 6:14-15", "Mt 18:21-35", "Eph 4:32", "Col 3:13"]

q-127:
  question: "What is the sixth petition?"
  answer:
    - "And lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one, that is: By ourselves we are too weak to hold our own even for a moment. ^1 And our sworn enemies – the devil, ^2 the world, ^3 and our own flesh ^4 – do not cease to attack us. ^5"
    - "Ever keep us strong with the power of your Holy Spirit, so that we may not be defeated but may stand firm against them, until we finally triumph. ^6"
  refs:
    - ["Ps 103:14-16", "Jn 15:5", "Rom 8:26", "Rom 8:35-39"]
    - ["2 Cor 2:11", "Eph 6:10-13", "1 Pet 5:8"]
    - ["Jn 15:18-21", "Eph 6:12", "1 Jn 5:19"]
    - ["Rom 7:23", "Gal 5:17"]
    - ["Mt 26:41", "1 Pet 5:8-9"]
    - ["Mt 10:19-20", "Rom 16:25-27", "1 Cor 10:13", "2 Cor 12:9", "Eph 6:10-13", "2 Thess 3:3"]

q-128:
  question: "How do you close this prayer?"
  answer:
    - "For yours is the kingdom and the power and the glory forever. Amen."
  refs: []

q-129:
  question: "What is the meaning of the word 'Amen'?"
  answer:
    - "'Amen' means: This shall truly and surely be! ^1 For my prayer is more certainly heard by God than I feel in my heart that I desire these things from him. ^2"
  refs:
    - ["2 Cor 1:20", "2 Tim 2:13"]
    - ["Is 65:24", "Jer 32:27", "Mt 7:7-8", "Lk 11:9-10"]
